I'm a pediatrician and an anesthesiologist,
أنا طبيب أطفال وطبيب تخدير
so I put children to sleep for a living.
اي اقوم بتنويم الاطفال لكسب عيشي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I'm an academic, so I put audiences to sleep for free.
وانا اكاديمي, اي اقوم بتنويم المستمعين بالمجان
But what I actually mostly do
ولكن في واقع الامر اكثر ما اقوم بعمله هو
is I manage the pain management service
ادارة خدمة التحكم في الالم
at the Packard Children's Hospital up at Stanford in Palo Alto.
في مستشفى باكارد للأطفال في جامعة ستانفورد في بالو ألتو
And it's from the experience
ومن خبرتي
from about 20 or 25 years of doing that
وبعد حوالي 20 او 25 سنه وانا اعمل في هذا المجال
that I want to bring to you the message this morning,
اريد ان انقل لكم رساله هذا الصباح
that pain is a disease.
انا الالم عباره عن مرض
Now most of the time,
الان في اغلب الاوقات
you think of pain as a symptom of a disease,
تظنون ان الالم عرض لمرض ما
and that's true most of the time.
وهذا صحيح في معظم الاوقات
It's the symptom of a tumor or an infection
فهو عرض لتورم او عدوى
or an inflammation or an operation.
او التهاب او عمليه جراحيه
But about 10 percent of the time,
ولكن لحوالي 10% من الاوقات
after the patient has recovered from one of those events,
عندما يتعالج المريض من اي من تلك الحالات
pain persists.
فان الالم يستمر
It persists for months
يستمر لعدة اشهر
and oftentimes for years,
وفي اكثر الاحوال لسنوات
and when that happens,
و عندما يحدث ذلك
it is its own disease.
يصبح الالم مرض بذاته
And before I tell you about how it is that we think that happens
وقبل ان اخبركم كيف نعتقد بان هذا يحدث
and what we can do about it,
وماذا نفعل حيال ذلك
I want to show you how it feels for my patients.
اريد ان اوضح لكم كيف يبدو ذلك لمرضاي
So imagine, if you will,
تخيل, اذا امكن
that I'm stroking your arm with this feather,
انني امسح علي ذراعك بهذه الريشه
as I'm stroking my arm right now.
كما افعل الان بذراعي
Now, I want you to imagine
الان اريدكم ان تتخيلوا
that I'm stroking it with this.
انني امسح عليها بهذا
Please keep your seat.
رجاءا ابقوا علي مقاعدكم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
A very different feeling.
احساس مختلف تماما
Now what does it have to do with chronic pain?
الان ما علاقة هذا بالالم المزمن؟
Imagine, if you will, these two ideas together.
تخيل هاتين الفكرتين سويا
Imagine what your life would be like
تخيل كيف ستكون حياتك
if I were to stroke it with this feather,
اذا كنت تمسح ذراعك بهذه الريشه
but your brain was telling you
ولكن عقلك يخبرك
that this is what you are feeling --
ان هذا ما تشعر به...
and that is the experience of my patients with chronic pain.
وتلك هي تجربة مرضاي مع الالم المزمن
In fact, imagine something even worse.
في الواقع, تخيل شئ اسوأ من ذلك
Imagine I were to stroke your child's arm with this feather,
تخيل انني امسح علي ذراع طفلك بهذه الريشه
and their brain [was] telling them
وعقله يخبره
that they were feeling this hot torch.
بانه يشعر بهذه الشعله الساخنه
That was the experience of my patient, Chandler,
تلك كانت تجربه مريضتي (شاندرل)
whom you see in the photograph.
التي تشاهدونها علي هذه الصوره
As you can see, she's a beautiful, young woman.
كما تشاهدون, امرأه شابه, جميله
She was 16 years old last year when I met her,
كانت في السادسة عشر من العمر عندما قابلتها العام السابق
and she aspired to be a professional dancer.
وكانت تطمح الي ان تصبح راقصه محترفه
And during the course of one of her dance rehearsals,
وخلال احد دروس تدريب الرقص
she fell on her outstretched arm and sprained her wrist.
سقطت علي ذراعها الممدودة مما ادى الي التواء معصمها
Now you would probably imagine, as she did,
الان من المرجح ان تتخيل, كما فعلت هي,
that a wrist sprain is a trivial event
ان التواء المعصم شئ بسيط
in a person's life.
في حياة الانسان
Wrap it in an ACE bandage,
لفها بالضماده المرنه المضادة للميكروبات (ايس)
take some ibuprofen for a week or two,
تناول بعض من مسكن الالم (الايبروفين) لمدة اسبوع او اثنين
and that's the end of the story.
وهذه هي نهايه المشكله.
But in Chandler's case, that was the beginning of the story.
ولكن في حالة (شاندرل), كانت تلك بداية المشكله
This is what her arm looked like
هذا ما كان يبدو عليه ذراعها
when she came to my clinic about three months after her sprain.
عندما حضرت الي عيادتي بعد ثلاثة اشهر من حادثة الالتواء
You can see that the arm is discolored,
يمكنكم ان تروا ان الذراع قد تشوه
purplish in color.
اخذ اللون الأرجواني
It was cadaverically cold to the touch.
كانت باردة ومتأكلة كالجيفة
The muscles were frozen, paralyzed --
العضلات قد تجمدت, شُلت
dystonic is how we refer to that.
ديستونيك(اضطراب الحركات العصبية ) هو ما نعبر به عن هذه الحالة
The pain had spread from her wrist to her hands,
انتشر الالم من معصمها الي كل يدها
to her fingertips, from her wrist up to her elbow,
الى اطراف اصابعها, من معصمها الى كوع اليد
almost all the way to her shoulder.
تقريبا كل يدها الي كتفها
But the worst part was,
و لكن الاسوأ من ذلك
not the spontaneous pain that was there 24 hours a day.
لم يكن الالم الموضعي المستمر طوال ال 24 ساعه على مدار اليوم
The worst part was that she had allodynia,
الجزء الاسوأ انها اصيبت ب الودينيا (الالم الناتج من محفز ),
the medical term for the phenomenon that I just illustrated
هذا هو التعبير الطبي للظاهرة التي شرحتها انفا
with the feather and with the torch.
بالريشة والشعلة.
The lightest touch of her arm --
اي لمسة خفيفة لذراعها --
the touch of a hand,
كلمسة من يد,
the touch even of a sleeve, of a garment, as she put it on --
اولمسة الكم, او الرداء حين تلبسه --
caused excruciating, burning pain.
يصيبها بألم موجع وحارق.
How can the nervous system get this so wrong?
كيف يمكن للجهاز العصبي ان يخطئ؟
How can the nervous system
كيف يمكن للجهاز العصبي
misinterpret an innocent sensation
ان يخطئ تفسير لمسة خفيفة
like the touch of a hand
كلمسة اليد مثلا
and turn it into the malevolent sensation
وحولها الى احساس موجع
of the touch of the flame?
كأنها لمسة شعلة
Well you probably imagine that the nervous system in the body
لربما تتخيلون الجهاز العصبي في الجسم
is hardwired like your house.
انه يشبه الاسلاك الكهربائية في منازلكم.
In your house, wires run in the wall,
في منازلكم. الاسلاك ممددة على الجدار,
from the light switch to a junction box in the ceiling
من مفتاح الضوء الى علبة التوزيع في السقف
and from the junction box to the light bulb.
ومن علبة التوزيع الى المصباح الضوئي.
And when you turn the switch on, the light goes on.
وعندما تضع المفتاح الضوئي في وضع التشغيل. يضيئ المصباح.
And when you turn the switch off, the light goes off.
وعندم تغلق المفتاح ينطفئ الضوء.
So people imagine the nervous system is just like that.
لذا يعتقد الناس ان الجهاز العصبي يشابهه.
If you hit your thumb with a hammer,
لو أنك ضربت ابهامك بالمطرقة,
these wires in your arm -- that, of course, we call nerves --
تلك الاسلاك في ذراعك-- والتي بطبيعة الحال تسمى اعصاب--
transmit the information into the junction box in the spinal cord
تبعث المعلومات الى علبة التوزيع في الحبل الشوكي
where new wires, new nerves,
حيث تقوم اعصاب جديدة
take the information up to the brain
باخذ المعلومات وارسالها للمخ
where you become consciously aware that your thumb is now hurt.
حيث تدرك ان ابهامك يتألم.
But the situation, of course, in the human body
لكن الوضع بطبيعة الحال في جسم الانسان
is far more complicated than that.
هو اشد تعقيدا من ذلك.
Instead of it being the case
بدلا من ان يكون هذا هو الحال
that that junction box in the spinal cord
ان علبة التوزيع توجد في الحبل الشوكي
is just simple where one nerve connects with the next nerve
هي ببساطة عبارة عن عصب مرتبط بالعصب المجاور
by releasing these little brown packets
بتحرير تلك الحزم الصغيرة ذات اللون البني
of chemical information called neurotransmitters
من المعلموات الكيميائية المسماة المرسلات العصبية
in a linear one-on-one fashion,
وبشكل خطي من نقطة لأخرى ,
in fact, what happens
في الحقيقة ان ما يحدث
is the neurotransmitters spill out in three dimensions --
ان تلك المرسلات العصبية تتفرق في ثلاثة ابعاد--
laterally, vertically, up and down in the spinal cord --
افقيا, عموديا, للاعلى وللاسفل في الحبل الشوكي--
and they start interacting
وتبدأ بالتفاعل
with other adjacent cells.
مع الخلايا الاخرى المجاورة.
These cells, called glial cells,
تلك الخلايا., تسمى الخلاية الدبقية,
were once thought to be
حيث كان يعتقد انها
unimportant structural elements of the spinal cord
عناصر بنائية قليلة الاهمية في الحبل الشوكي
that did nothing more than hold all the important things together,
ولا تقوم بشيئ يتجاوز ربط الاشياء المهمة مع بعضها البعض,
like the nerves.
كالاعصاب.
But it turns out
لكن أتضح لنا
the glial cells have a vital role
ان تلك الخلايا الدبقية لديها مهمة حيوية
in the modulation, amplification
في التعديل, التضخيم
and, in the case of pain, the distortion
و في حالة الالم التحريف
of sensory experiences.
للخبرات الحسية.
These glial cells become activated.
تلك الخلايا الدبقية تصبح مفعلة.
Their DNA starts to synthesize new proteins,
الحمض النووي الخاص بها يبدأ في توليف بروتينات جديدة,
which spill out
والتي تقوم بالتفرق
and interact with adjacent nerves,
وتتفاعل مع الاعصاب المجاورة.
and they start releasing their neurotransmitters,
وتبدأ بتحرير مرسلاتها العصبية.
and those neurotransmitters spill out
وتلك المرسلات العصبية تتفرق
and activate adjacent glial cells, and so on and so forth,
وتفعل الخلايا الدبقية المجاورة وهكذا دواليك,
until what we have
حتى نحصل على
is a positive feedback loop.
على دائرة رد فعل ايجابي
It's almost as if somebody came into your home
ان ذلك يشابه تماما كم لو ان شخصا اتى الى منزلك
and rewired your walls
واعاد ربط الاسلاك في الحوائط,
so that the next time you turned on the light switch,
بحيث انك عندم تشغل مفتاح الاضاءة ,
the toilet flushed three doors down,
ينفتح السيفون وتغلق ثلاثة ابواب,
or your dishwasher went on,
و تشتغل غسالة الاطباق الخاصة بك,
or your computer monitor turned off.
او تطفأ شاشة حاسبك الآلي.
That's crazy,
ذلك جنون,
but that's, in fact, what happens
لكن ذلك بالفعل ما يحصل
with chronic pain.
في الالم المزمن.
And that's why pain becomes its own disease.
وذلك ما يجعل الالم يصبح مرضا مستقلا بذاته
The nervous system has plasticity.
الجهاز العصبي لديه مرونة
It changes, and it morphs
انه يتغير, ويقرأ
in response to stimuli.
مستجيبا للمحفزات
Well, what do we do about that?
حسنا ,مالذي فعلناه تجاه ذلك؟
What can we do in a case like Chandler's?
مالذي يمكننا عمله في حالة تشبه حالة شاندرل؟
We treat these patients in a rather crude fashion
نحن نتعامل مع تلك النوعية من المرضى بشكل جاف
at this point in time.
وفي هذه اللحظة من الزمان
We treat them with symptom-modifying drugs --
نعالجهم بادوية تحويل الاعراض--
painkillers --
قاتلات الام--
which are, frankly, not very effective
والتي هي بصراحة غير فعالة
for this kind of pain.
لهذا النوع من الالم.
We take nerves that are noisy and active
نأخذ تلك الاعصاب المزعجة والنشيطة
that should be quiet,
والتي يجب ان تلتزم الهدوء,
and we put them to sleep with local anesthetics.
ونجعلها تخلد للنوم باستخدام مخدر محلي
And most importantly, what we do
واهم شئ نفعله
is we use a rigorous, and often uncomfortable, process
اننا نتبع نهج صارم وغالبا غير مريح
of physical therapy and occupational therapy
من العلاج الطبيعي والعلاج الطبي
to retrain the nerves in the nervous system
لاعادة الاعصاب في الجهاز العصبي
to respond normally
لجعلها تستجيب بشكل طبيعي
to the activities and sensory experiences
للنشاطات والتجارب الاحساسية
that are part of everyday life.
والتي هي جزء من الحياة اليومية.
And we support all of that
وندعم كل ماسبق
with an intensive psychotherapy program
ببرنامج علاج نفسي مكثف
to address the despondency, despair and depression
لتخطي الاكتئاب, واليأس, والجزع
that always accompanies
الذي غالبا ما يصاحب
severe, chronic pain.
الالم المزمن الحاد.
It's successful,
كان ذلك ناجحا,
as you can see from this video of Chandler,
كما تشاهدون من خلال هذ المقطع لشاندلر,
who, two months after we first met her,
بعد شهرين من لقائي بها,
is now doings a back flip.
تقوم هنا بشقلبتها الخلفية.
And I had lunch with her yesterday
وتناولت الغداء معها بالأمس,
because she's a college student studying dance at Long Beach here,
لأنها طالبة جامعية تدرس الرقص هنا في لونغ بيتش.
and she's doing absolutely fantastic.
وهي تتقدم بشكل مذهل
But the future is actually even brighter.
لكن المستقبل سيكون اكثر اشراقا
The future holds the promise
يحمل لنا المستقبل وعدا
that new drugs will be developed
بانه سوف يتم تطوير ادوية جديدة
that are not symptom-modifying drugs
حيث لن تكون الادوية مجرد مغيرات للاعراض
that simply mask the problem,
و تقوم ببساطة تقوم بوضع قناع على المشكلة,
as we have now,
كما نفعل الان,
but that will be disease-modifying drugs
ولكنها سوف تكون ادوية محولات للمرض
that will actually go right to the root of the problem
والتي سوف تتجه مباشرة الى جذر المشكلة
and attack those glial cells,
وتهاجم تلك الخلايا الدبقية,
or those pernicious proteins
او تلك البروتينات الضارة
that the glial cells elaborate,
والتي تنتجها الخلايا الدبقية
that spill over and cause this central nervous system wind-up,
والتي تنتشر مما يجعل الجهاز العصبي يختل
or plasticity,
اويصبح لدنا
that so is capable
ويكون قادرا
of distorting and amplifying
على تضخيم وتشويه
the sensory experience that we call pain.
التجارب الاحساسية التي نسميها بالألم
So I have hope
لذلك لدي امل
that in the future,
انه في المستقبل
the prophetic words of George Carlin will be realized,
سوف تتحقق نبؤات جورج كارلين
who said, "My philosophy:
والذي قال, "فلسفتي :
No pain, no pain."
لا ألم, لا ألم"
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)